# **Filippos Fotiadis**

Peter O'Donnell Building, Office 5.412, 201 E 24th St, Austin, TX 78712, USA

fotiadisff.github.io

ffotiadis@utexas.edu

(+1) 470 3345545

## **RESEARCH INTERESTS**

My primary research interests lie in the intersection of control theory, optimization, and machine learning, with applications to security, autonomy, and verification of cyber-physical systems. I specifically focus on two research directions: creating game- and optimization-based decision-making tools to render cyber-physical systems secure against adversaries; and developing learning-based as well as approximation-free control methods to increase their resilience under environmental and model uncertainty.

### **EDUCATION**

<b>Ph.D. in Aerospace Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology</b> (GPA 4.0/4.0) Thesis title: "Game-Theoretic Learning and Control for Resilience of Complex Adaptive Systems" Advisor: Prof. Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis	2019-2024
M.S. in Mathematics, Georgia Institute of Technology (GPA 4.0/4.0)	2019-2023
M.S. in Aerospace Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology (GPA 4.0/4.0)	2019-2022
Diploma (B.S. & M.S.) in Electrical & Computer Engineering, Aristotle University of Thessaloniki (GPA 9.59/10)	2013-2018
Thesis title: "Improving Robustness of Adaptive Dynamic Programming Controllers using Prescribed Performance Control" Advisor: Prof. George A. Rovithakis	

## PROFESSIONAL & RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Researcher, University of Texas at Austin Autonomous Systems Group (PI: Prof. Ufuk Topcu)	Aug 2024-present
Graduate Research Assistant, Georgia Institute of Technology Intelligent Cyber-Physical Systems Lab (PI: Prof. Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis)	Aug 2019-Aug 2024
Undergraduate Researcher, Aristotle University of Thessaloniki Automation and Robotics Lab (PI: Prof. George A. Rovithakis)	Feb 2018-Nov 2018
Intern on Physical Human-Robot Interaction, The Centre for Research and Technology Hellas Automation and Robotics Lab (PI: Prof. Zoe Doulgeri)	Jul 2017-Sep 2017
TEACHING EXPERIENCE	

Automation and Robotics Lab (PI: Prof. George A. Rovithakis)	
Intern on Physical Human-Robot Interaction, The Centre for Research and Technology Hellas Automation and Robotics Lab (PI: Prof. Zoe Doulgeri)	Jul 2017-Sep 2017
TEACHING EXPERIENCE	
Instructor, AE8750/8751 Robotics Research Fundamentals Department of Aerospace Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology	Spring 2023
Assistant in Teaching, AE8803 Optimization-Based Learning Control and Games Department of Aerospace Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology	Fall 2022, Fall 2023
SCHOLARSHIPS	
Georgia Tech Aerospace Engineering Fellowship (based on exemplary performance) Alexander S. Onassis Foundation Scholarship Gerondelis Foundation Graduate Study Scholarship	Aug 2023-Aug 2024 Sep 2020-May 2024 2021
AWARDS & HONORS	

Outstanding Reviewer of the IEEE Control Systems Letters	2023
Excellent Reviewer for the Journal of Guidance, Control, and Dynamics	2022

### **PUBLICATIONS**

#### **Books**

 A. Kanellopoulos, L. Zhai, F. Fotiadis, K. G. Vamvoudakis, "Control and Game Theoretic Methods for Cyber-Physical Security," to appear in *Elsevier*, 2024.

### **Book Chapters**

1. **F. Fotiadis**, L. Zhai, K. G. Vamvoudakis, J. Hugues, "On the Impact of Sensor-Actuator Clock Offsets on Off-Policy Reinforcement Learning," to appear in *Smarter Cyber-Physical Systems: Enabling Methodologies and Applications*, eds. Y. Wan, K. G. Vamvoudakis, Y. Chen, F. L. Lewis, CRC Press, 2024.

#### **Journal Publications**

- 1. F. Fotiadis, K. G. Vamvoudakis, "Input-Output Data-Driven Sensor Selection for Cyber-Physical Systems," submitted.
- 2. **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, "A Physics-Informed Learning Framework to Solve the Infinite-Horizon Optimal Control Problem," submitted.
- 3. S. Niu, A. Bouland, H. Wang, **F. Fotiadis**, A. Kurdila, A. L'Afflitto, S. T. Paruchuri, K. G. Vamvoudakis, "Convergence Rates of Online Critic Value Function Approximation in Native Spaces," to appear in *IEEE Control Systems Letters*, 2024.
- 4. **F. Fotiadis**, A. Kanellopoulos, K. G. Vamvoudakis, J. Hugues, "On the Effect of Clock Offsets and Quantization on Learning-based Adversarial Games," *Automatica*, vol. 167, paper 111762, 2024.
- 5. **F. Fotiadis**, G. A. Rovithakis, "Input-Constrained Prescribed Performance Control for High-order MIMO Uncertain Nonlinear Systems via Reference Modification," *IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control*, vol. 69, no. 5, pp. 3301-3308, 2024.
- 6. **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, Z.-P. Jiang, "<u>Data-Driven Actuator Allocation for Actuator Redundant Systems</u>," *IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control*, vol. 69, no. 4, pp. 2249-2264, 2024.
- 7. **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, "<u>Learning-based Actuator Selection for Increased Attack Resilience of Uncertain Systems</u>," *Automatica*, vol. 159, paper 111332, 2024.
- 8. **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, "<u>Recursive Reasoning with Reduced Complexity and Intermittency for Non-Equilibrium Learning in Stochastic Games</u>," *IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems*, vol. 34, no. 11, pp. 8467-8481, 2023.
- 9. **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, "Concurrent Receding Horizon Control and Estimation against Stealthy Attacks," *IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control*, vol. 68, no. 6, pp. 3712-3719, 2023.
- 10. K. G. Vamvoudakis, **F. Fotiadis**, A. Kanellopoulos, N.-M. T. Kokolakis, "<u>Nonequilibrium Dynamical Games: A Control Systems Perspective</u>," *Annual Reviews in Control*, vol. 53, pp. 6-18, 2022.
- 11. **F. Fotiadis**, G. A. Rovithakis, "Prescribed Performance Control for Discontinuous Output Reference Tracking," *IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control*, vol. 66, no. 9, pp. 4409-4416, 2021.
- 12. **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, "<u>Detection of Actuator Faults for Continuous-Time Systems with Intermittent State Feedback</u>," *Systems and Control Letters*, vol. 152, pp. 104938, 2021.

#### **Conference Publications**

- 1. N. Tukenmez, **F. Fotiadis**, J. M. Magalhães Júnior, K. G. Vamvoudakis, S. Bogosyan, "Intermittent Learning for Trajectory Tracking Control with an Experimental Validation on Microdrones," submitted.
- 2. **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, "Input-Output Data-Driven Sensor Selection," to appear in *IEEE Conference on Decision and Control*, Milan, Italy, 2024.
- 3. **F. Fotiadis**, G. A. Rovithakis, K. G. Vamvoudakis, "Embedding Learning-based Optimal Controllers with Assured Safety," to appear in *IEEE Conference on Decision and Control*, Milan, Italy, 2024.
- 4. A. Kanellopoulos, **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, H. Sandberg, "Unpredictable Switching for Cyber-Physical Security Against Worst-case Attackers," to appear in *IEEE Conference on Decision and Control*, Milan, Italy, 2024.
- 5. N. Tukenmez, **F. Fotiadis**, J. M. Magalhães Júnior, K. G. Vamvoudakis, S. Bogosyan, "Reward Drops in Learning-based Control with an Experimental Validation on Microdrones," to appear in *IEEE Conference on Decision and Control*, Milan, Italy, 2024.
- 6. **F. Fotiadis**, A. Kanellopoulos, K. G. Vamvoudakis, J. Hugues, "Poisoning Actuation Attacks Against the Learning of an Optimal Controller," to appear in *American Control Conference*, Toronto, Canada, 2024.
- 7. S. Athalye, **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, J. Hugues, "An Output Feedback Game-Theoretic Approach for Defense against Stealthy GNSS Spoofing Attacks," to appear in *American Control Conference*, Toronto, Canada, 2024.

- 8. J. M. Magalhães Júnior, L. Zhai, **F. Fotiadis**, A. Kanellopoulos, K. G. Vamvoudakis, J. Hugues, "<u>Real-Time and Experimental Reactive and Proactive Defense in a Multi-Agent Scenario</u>," *Proc. AIAA SciTech Forum*, Orlando, Florida, 2024
- 9. **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, "<u>A Physics-Informed Neural Networks Framework to Solve the Infinite-Horizon Optimal Control Problem</u>," *Proc. IEEE Conference on Decision and Control*, pp. 6008-6013, Marina Bay Sands, Singapore, 2023.
- 10. **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, "<u>Game-Theoretic Deception Methods for Perfectly and Bounded Rational Stealthy Attackers</u>," *Proc. IEEE Conference on Decision and Control*, pp. 7956-7963, Marina Bay Sands, Singapore, 2023.
- 11. **F. Fotiadis**, G. A. Rovithakis, "<u>Input-Constrained Prescribed Performance Control for SISO Nonlinear Systems via Reference Relaxation</u>," *Proc. Mediterranean Conference on Control and Automation*, pp. 777-782, Limassol, Cyprus, 2023.
- 12. K. G. Vamvoudakis, **F. Fotiadis**, J. P. Hespanha, R. Chinchilla, G. Yang, M. Liu, J. S. Shamma, L. Pavel, "Game Theory for Autonomy: From Min-Max Optimization to Equilibrium and Bounded Rationality Learning," *Proc. American Control Conference*, pp. 4363-4380, San Diego, CA, 2023.
- 13. L. Zhai, **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, J. Hugues, "<u>Timing-Aware Resilience of Data-driven Off-policy Reinforcement Learning for Discrete-Time Systems</u>," *Proc. American Control Conference*, pp. 2782-2787, San Diego, CA, 2023.
- 14. L. Zhai, A. Kanellopoulos, **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, J. Hugues, "A Modular Approach to Verification of Learning Components in Cyber-Physical Systems," *Proc. AIAA SciTech, National Harbor*, MD, 2023.
- 15. **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, Z.-P. Jiang, "<u>Data-Based Actuator Selection for Optimal Control Allocation</u>," *Proc. IEEE Conference on Decision and Control*, pp. 4674-4679, Cancun, Mexico, 2022.
- 16. **F. Fotiadis**, A. Kanellopoulos, K. G. Vamvoudakis, J. Hugues, "<u>Impact of Sensor and Actuator Clock Offsets on Reinforcement Learning</u>," *Proc. American Control Conference*, pp. 2669-2674, Atlanta, GA, 2022.
- 17. L. Zhai, A. Kanellopoulos, **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, J. Hugues, "<u>Towards Intelligent Security for Unmanned Aerial Vehicles: A Taxonomy of Attacks, Faults, and Detection Mechanisms</u>," *Proc. AIAA SciTech Forum*, 2022.
- 18. **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, "Learning-based Actuator Placement for Uncertain Systems," *Proc. IEEE Conference on Decision and Control*, pp. 90-95, Austin, TX, 2021.
- 19. **F. Fotiadis**, C. Verginis, K. G. Vamvoudakis, U. Topcu, "<u>Assured Learning-based Optimal Control subject to Timed Temporal Logic Constraints</u>," *Proc. IEEE Conference on Decision and Control*, pp. 750-756, Austin, TX, 2021.
- 20. A. Kanellopoulos, F. Fotiadis, C. Sun, Z. Xu, K. G. Vamvoudakis, U. Topcu, W. E. Dixon, "Temporal Logic-based Intermittent, Optimal, and Safe Continuous-Time Learning for Trajectory Tracking," Proc. IEEE Conference on Decision and Control, pp. 1263-1268, Austin, TX, 2021.
- 21. **F. Fotiadis**, K. G. Vamvoudakis, "<u>Recursive Reasoning for Bounded Rationality in Multi-Agent Non-Equilibrium Play Learning Systems</u>," *Proc. IEEE Conference on Control Technology and Applications*, pp. 741-746, San Diego, CA, 2021.
- 22. A. Kanellopoulos, **F. Fotiadis** K. G. Vamvoudakis, V. Gupta, "<u>A Meta-Learning and Bounded Rationality Framework for Repeated Games in Adversarial Environments</u>," *Proc. IEEE Conference on Decision and Control*, pp. 1640-1645, Jeju Island, Republic of Korea, 2020.
- 23. **F. Fotiadis**, A. Kanellopoulos, K. G. Vamvoudakis, "Constrained Differential Games for Secure Decision-Making against Stealthy Attacks," *Proc. American Control Conference*, pp. 4658-4663, Denver, CO, 2020.
- 24. F. Dimeas, **F. Fotiadis**, D. Papageorgiou, A. Sidiropoulos, Z. Doulgeri, "<u>Towards Progressive Automation of Repetitive Tasks</u> Through Physical Human-Robot Interaction," Human Friendly Robotics: 10th International Workshop, pp. 151-163, 2018.

#### **SERVICE ACTIVITIES**

**Reviewer, Journals** 

Neurocomputing

#### Automatica (>40) 2019-2024 IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control (>40) 2020-2021, 2023-2024 IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man and Cybernetics: Systems (>20) 2020-2024 IEEE Control Systems Letters (>20) 2020-2021, 2023-2024 IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems 2021-2024 **IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics** 2023 IEEE Transactions on Control of Network Systems 2021 IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics 2023-2024 IEEE Transactions on Artificial Intelligence 2021 IEEE Transactions on Control Systems Technology 2020 International Journal of Robust and Nonlinear Control 2022-2023 Systems & Control Letters 2023 European Journal of Control 2024 AIAA Journal of Guidance, Control, and Dynamics 2022

2023

Journal of Optimization Theory and Applications	2020-2021
Expert Systems with Applications	2020
Optimal Control, Applications and Methods	2021-2022
Applied Mathematics and Computation	2023
The Aeronautical Journal	2023
Reviewer, Conferences	
IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC) (>20)	2020-2024
American Control Conference (ACC) (>10)	2020-2024
European Control Conference (ECC)	2023
IFAC World Congress	2021, 2023
Mediterranean Conference on Control and Automation (MED)	2023-2024
IEEE Conference on Control Technology and Applications (CCTA)	2020, 2022
IFAC Conference on Modelling, Identification and Control of Nonlinear Systems	2021

#### **TALKS & PRESENTATIONS**

- "A Physics-Informed Neural Networks Framework to Solve the Infinite-Horizon Optimal Control Problem" IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), Marina Bay Sands, Singapore, 2023 [Oral Presentation]
- "Game-Theoretic Deception Methods for Perfectly and Bounded Rational Stealthy Attackers" IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), Marina Bay Sands, Singapore, 2023 [Oral Presentation]
- "Game-Theoretic Learning and Control for Resilience of Complex Adaptive Systems" Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, USA, 2023 [PhD Proposal]
- "Input-Constrained Prescribed Performance Control for SISO Nonlinear Systems via Reference Relaxation" Mediterranean Conference on Control and Automation (MED), Limassol, Cyprus, 2023 [Oral Presentation]
- "Timing-Aware Resilience of Data-driven Off-policy Reinforcement Learning for Discrete-Time Systems" American Control Conference (ACC), San Diego, USA, 2023 [Oral Presentation]
- "Data-Based Actuator Selection for Optimal Control Allocation" IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), Cancun, Mexico, 2022 [Oral Presentation]
- "On Non-Equilibrium Learning in Stochastic Games" Combining Learning and Control in Cyber-Physical Systems Workshop, IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), Cancun, Mexico, 2022 [Poster Presentation]
- "Learning-Based Actuator Placement and Allocation for Resilience against Attacks" N.C. A&T State University, Greensboro, USA, 2022 [Oral Presentation Invited Talk]
- "Impact of Sensor and Actuator Clock Offsets on Reinforcement Learning" American Control Conference (ACC), Atlanta, USA, 2022 [Rapid Interactive Presentation]
- "Learning-based Actuator Placement for Uncertain Systems" IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), Austin, USA, 2021 [Oral Presentation (Virtual)]
- "Assured Learning-based Optimal Control subject to Timed Temporal Logic Constraints" IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), Austin, USA, 2021 [Oral Presentation (Virtual)]
- "Recursive Reasoning for Bounded Rationality in Multi-Agent Non-Equilibrium Play Learning Systems" IEEE Conference on Control Technology and Applications (CCTA), San Diego, USA, 2021 [Oral Presentation (Virtual)]
- "Constrained Differential Games for Secure Decision-Making against Stealthy Attacks", American Control Conference (ACC), Denver, USA, 2020 [Oral Presentation (Virtual)]